Guide to the Family Counseling of Greater New Haven, Inc. Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Family Counseling of Greater New Haven, Inc. records
1881-2000
MS 1808
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9
The Family Counseling of Greater New Haven, Inc. records document the administrative history of a local social welfare agency from 1881 to 2000. The records consist largely of annual reports and minute records of the board of directors, other sub-committee minute records and reports, financial, fund raising records, correspondence, case files, newsletters, New Haven Register column "What's Your Problem?," scrapbooks, photographs and slides.
Family Counseling of Greater New Haven, Inc
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Family Counseling of Greater New Haven, Inc., 2002.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Annual Reports and Meeting Minutes, 1881-1993. II. Administrative Records, 1887-2000. III. Outreach and Publicity, 1953-2000.
Scope and Contents
The Family Counseling of Greater New Haven, Inc. (FCGNH) records document the administrative history of a local social welfare agency from 1881 to 2000. The early organization began as a philanthropic society but became a professional social service agency. In contrast to other social service agencies in other states, prominent male community leaders formed and ran the FCGNH, but as it shifted to a professional social service agency in the 1920s, the board hired female social workers and home visitors. The professionalization of social work grew out of the settlement house movement and was institutionalized at the national level when Congress established the Children's Bureau, in the Department of Labor, to address maternal and children's health. Together, the settlement house movement and the Children's Bureau promoted social work through new professional programs at the university level, which in turn, shaped the social service mission of the FCGNH. The records of the FCGNH provide a regional example of the success of the Children's Bureau to promote local state agencies committed to child and family welfare during the Progressive Era and post war years. At the local level, the records document the hardships of social change, poverty, and family breakdown caused by industrialization, immigration, economics, and war. These records further reveal the difficulties the organization faced in maintaining welfare-based services with limited resources.
Biographical / Historical
The Family Counseling of Greater New Haven, Inc. (FCGNH) provided welfare and social services for 124 years to New Haven County. The organization underwent significant transformations, including several name changes during its history: Organized Charities Society (1878-1887); Organized Charities Association (1888-1929); Family Society of New Haven (1930-1945); Family Service of New Haven (1946-1971); and Family Counseling of Greater New Haven, Inc. (1972-2002).
The group that became known as the FCGNH was first established in 1878 under the name Organized Charities Society, but within a few years adopted the name Organized Charities Association (OCA). Francis Wayland, dean of the Yale Law School, served as the president of the organization for its first twenty-five years. The OCA initially formed as an emergency measure to deal with the growing population of unemployed transients. Within a few years, the OCA shifted emphasis from the unemployed to providing relief to the "worthy" poor in the form of food and fuel assistance, housing, and employment. It also served as the clearinghouse for charity organizations in New Haven. By 1881, the organization adopted the functions and goals of the Charity Organization Society, which began in London in 1869. This society sought to teach families how to be self-sufficient, educate the community in the "correct" principles of relief, and eradicate poverty. The OCA became the second non-sectarian Charity Organization Society in the United States. It instituted home visiting and sent out visiting agents to the poor, and in many cases recommended the removal of children to orphanages and correctional facilities.
By the early twentieth century, the OCA shifted from a benevolent society to a professional family relief organization. The first visiting nurse joined the staff in 1913, and the Case Study Committee was formed to supervise the work of "friendly" visitors and to discuss individual cases. World War I and the influenza epidemic marked the reorganization of the society, as the demands for family casework service increased. By the 1920s, a small staff of trained social workers assumed casework responsibilities. As the society professionalized, the OCA joined nationally recognized social work organizations, including the American Association for Organizing Family Social Work, the National Social Workers' Exchange and the American Association for Social Work. Reflecting the new emphasis on family casework, the organization changed names to the Family Society of New Haven in 1930, and in 1946 it became the Family Service of New Haven (FSNH). Between 1935 and 1955 a number of new programs, including psychiatric consultation and group therapy were added, and the "Supervised Homemaker Services Program" was implemented in 1943 to address maternal and child health cases. By the 1960s, the FSNH increased its role in the community by offering services to the inner city and offered advice through the "What's Your Problem?" column in the New Haven Register.
In the late 1960s, FSNH worked collaboratively with Community Progress, Inc. to provide mental health services to New Haven as well as other communities in the state. FSNH received a number of inquiries from local cities to establish branch offices to meet the growing demand for mental health services. In the 1970s, the board of directors received funding from Orange, Guilford, and Madison, which led to the formation of branch offices in these towns. New programs aimed at youth services, parenting, child abuse, crisis intervention, and rehabilitation for developmentally disabled adults were added and the FCGNH became a licensed psychiatric clinic. By the 1990s, substance abuse programs and employee assistance programs were established. Long standing financial problems, however, plagued the organization and in 2002 the board of directors permanently ended 124 years of "unbroken service."
Charities; Child health services; Family counseling; Maternal health services; Mental health services; Social service; New Haven (Conn.); New Haven County (Conn.); Community Progress, Inc; Family Counseling of Greater New Haven, Inc; Family Service of New Haven; Organized Charities Association; Organized Charities Society
- Annual Reports and Meeting Minutes, 1881-1993, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The Annual Reports and Meeting Minutes are arranged in four sections by organization name: Section one, Organized Charities Association (1888-1929); Section Two, Family Society of New Haven (1930-1945); Section three, Family Service of New Haven (1946-1971); and Section four, Family Counseling of Greater New Haven, Inc. (1972-2002). The files include bound annual reports from 1881 to 1928 and loose annual reports that duplicate some of the bound annual reports, but include photographs, appendices, and advertisements. The annual reports provide a chronological history of the organization, sporadic individual caseworker reports, revenue and investment statements, graphs, and statistical reports outlining the type of cases handled, services provided, and the nationality and gender of the recipients. The meeting minutes cover the years 1930 to 1993 and provide brief summaries of meeting agendas, executive board decisions, subcommittee reports and recommendations for funding new programs. Of particular interest, the minute records describe the various name changes of the organization and provide some discussion on the rational for these changes.
  Materials filed under Family Service of New Haven (FSNH) include subcommittee records that document the activities of the organization from 1946 to 1975. The Case Study Committee records are the most substantive in documenting individual family casework, and provide caseworker summaries that include information on the size of the family, ethnicity, the primary problems faced by the families and caseworker recommendations. Researchers will also find minute records from the Community Progress Inc.--Family Service of New Haven Hill Project, which administered a group therapy program for teenage girls living in East Rock between 1965 to 1966.
  Of equal interest are the New Haven Coalition of Suburban Taxpayers for Welfare Reform minute records. This organization formed in 1970 to address the state welfare cutbacks and represented members from FSNH as well as United Way, the League of Women Voters, the Welfare Moms, Catholic Family Service and several other facilities impacted by state budget cuts.
  - Organized Charities Association
    - Bound annual reports, 1881-1928 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 2)
    - Loose annual reports, 1881-1882, 1888, 1892, 1895, 1897-1899, 1901-1903, 1905-1929 (Box 2, Folder 3 - 7)
    - Meeting minutes, 1919-1929 (Box 2, Folder 8 - 9)
  - Family Society of New Haven
    - Loose annual reports, 1930-1945 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Board of Directors meeting minutes
      - 1930 - 1935 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - 1936 Jan - 1946 Apr [includes first two board meetings under Family Service of New Haven] (Box 3, Folder 12 - 14)
  - Family Service of New Haven
    - Board of Directors meeting minutes
      - 1946 May -1970 Mar (Box 3, Folder 15 - 21)
      - 1970 Apr -1972 May (Box 4, Folder 22 - 24)
    - Subcommittee meeting minutes
      - Case Study Committee, 1947, 1951, 1960-1967 (Box 4, Folder 25 - 34)
      - Committee on Fees, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 35)
      - Community Progress, Inc.-- Family Service of New Haven Hill Project, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 36)
      - Family Services Agencies of Connecticut [overlap between FSNH and FCGNH], 1959, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 37)
      - Homemaking Advisor, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 38)
      - House Committee, 1963-1966 (Box 5, Folder 39)
      - New Haven Coalition of Urban and Suburban Taxpayers Welfare Reform, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 40 - 42)
      - Personnel Committee, 1954-1955, 1957-1968 (Box 5, Folder 43 - 50)
      - Public Issues Committee, 1955-1966 (Box 5, Folder 51 - 59)
      - Professional Services Committee, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 60)
      - United Fund Agencies, 1953-1963 (Box 5, Folder 61 - 63)
      - West Haven Common Nursery, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Family Counseling of Greater New Haven, Inc.
    - Board of Directors meeting minutes
      - 1972 June - 1975 Dec (Box 6, Folder 65 - 74)
      - 1976 Jan - 1981 Dec (Box 7, Folder 75 - 81)
      - 1982 Jan - 1987 Dec (Box 8, Folder 82 - 92)
      - 1988 Jan - 1993 Dec (Box 9, Folder 93 - 114)
    - Subcommittee meeting minutes
      - Development Committee, 1972-1974 (Box 10, Folder 115)
      - Guilford Advisory Committee, 1976-1977 (Box 10, Folder 116 - 117)
      - Madison Advisory Committee, 1975-1977 (Box 10, Folder 118 - 119)
- Administrative Records, 1887-2000, Series II
  The Administrative Records are arranged alphabetically by organization name and subject. The records are comprised of articles of incorporation, by-laws, correspondence, financial records, memoranda and announcements, personnel records, printed matter, position papers, and reports.
  The series contains general correspondence that is largely routine in nature, including requests for information, publications, and thank-you letters. There are two folders of correspondence of H. J. Mahew from 1925 to 1932. As general secretary, Mahew responded to community donations, offered recommendations for welfare services and in some cases enclosed copies of welfare summary statistics from the annual reports.
  Financial records document the continuous struggle to raise money for specific programs and reveal the importance of endowment funds and the struggle for local and national funding. The organization relied on the Marrett Fund and McClean Foundation, as well as funding from the city through the Community Chest and the United Way. Of particular interest, is the Family Counseling of Greater New Haven, Inc. (FCGNH) response to a United Way Subcommittee Report (2000), which documents the United Way's decision to suspend funding. In this report, the FCGNH outlines why the United Way should reconsider their decision and includes several folders of supporting attachments. The United Way cited multiple reasons for their decisions, but the predominate reason had to do with financial management and development. This report and the attachments provide important documentation on the funding history of the organization by the United Way. Unfortunately, the records lack a response from the United Way and it is not known whether they reversed their initial decision; nor can one follow the discussion through the minute records and correspondence, as they end in 1993 and 1994. The agency, however, faced intermittent financial problems over the course of its history, and funding problems described in this report reveal the mounting fiscal problems that led to the closure of the FCGNH in 2002.
  The series also includes a number of different reports related to specific agency programs. The two most significant are the Sunday Dinner reports (1932-1943) and the reports of the Community Progress, Inc.--Family Service of New Haven Hill Project. The agency sent meals to needy families on Sundays, and the reports describe individual family situations and rationalize why meals were offered. The Community Progress, Inc, (CPI) reports provide insight on the level of services offered based on the "deserving" status of the requesting family, and reflect some of the biases of the caseworkers in assessing the home environment. These reports document the collaborative efforts of the Family Service of New Haven with CPI to strengthen the community through employment programs and group treatment therapy programs during the 1960s and 1970s. One can also locate correspondence specific to the CPI Manpower Development and Training Project, which was initiated during the turbulence of redevelopment in the 1960s.
  - Organized Charities Association
    - Articles of Incorporation, 1887-1932 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Reports, 1898, 1922, 1925-1927 (Box 11, Folder 2 - 3)
  - Family Society of New Haven
    - By-laws, 1930 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence
      - General (A-W), 1927-1931 (Box 11, Folder 5 - 10)
      - Mahew, H. J. (general secretary), 1925-1932 (Box 11, Folder 11 - 12)
    - Financial records
      - Donations, 1924-1933 (Box 11, Folder 13)
      - Ellsworth Foote estate, 1924-1933 (Box 11, Folder 14)
      - Expense report, social work, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 15)
      - Legacies and bequests, 1878-1948 (Box 11, Folder 16)
      - List of state cases, 1932-1933 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Memoranda, 1925-1927, 1932-1933 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Printed matter, undated (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Reports
      - General, 1932-1933 (Box 11, Folder 20)
      - Sunday Dinner, 1932-1943 (Box 12, Folder 21 - 24)
  - Family Service of New Haven
    - Articles of Incorporation, 1948-1976 (Box 12, Folder 25 - 27)
    - Budget reports, 1953-1959 (Box 12, Folder 28)
    - Building and facilities, 1959-1964 (Box 12, Folder 29 - 31)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1948-1969,1971 (Box 12, Folder 32)
      - Community Progress, Inc., 1961-1964 (Box 12, Folder 33)
    - Financial records
      - Applications and grants, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 34)
      - Funding proposal, Connecticut Valley Hospital Services [admission records], 1964-1970 (Box 13, Folder 35 - 39)
      - Ruth Harris Escrow Fund, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 40)
      - Marrett Fund, 1959-1967 (Box 13, Folder 41 - 42)
      - McClean Foundation correspondence, 1959-1970 (Box 13, Folder 43 - 44)
      - News clippings [re: Community Progress Inc.], 1962-1963 (Box 13, Folder 45)
      - Public Act Funding Report, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 46)
      - Samuel and Aramina Schwartz Trust, 1954, 1965-1976 (Box 13, Folder 47 - 48)
    - Memoranda and announcements, 1956-1963, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 49 - 56)
    - Personnel
      - Job descriptions, 1961, 1962, 1964 (Box 14, Folder 57)
      - Salary ranges, 1950-1966 (Box 14, Folder 58 - 59)
      - Staff lists, 1972 (Box 14, Folder 60)
    - Reports
      - Community Progress, Inc.--Family Service of New Haven Hill Projects, 1961-1966 (Box 14, Folder 61 - 67)
    - Standing committee lists and contact sheets, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 68)
  - Family Counseling of Greater New Haven, Inc.
    - Articles of Association, 1972-1973, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 69)
    - Correspondence, 1991-1994 (Box 15, Folder 70 - 74)
    - Counselor surveys and intake forms, 1978-1986 (Box 15, Folder 75)
    - Financial Records
      - Budget and income reports, 1975-1983 (Box 15, Folder 76)
      - Funding report, United Way, 2000 (Box 15, Folder 77 - 79)
      - Memoranda, 1991-1994 (Box 15, Folder 80)
    - Personnel, Staff lists, 1973-1977 (Box 15, Folder 81 - 84)
    - Position paper on the protection of children and child abuse, undated (Box 15, Folder 85)
- Outreach and Publicity, 1953-2000, Series III
  The Outreach and Publicity records overlap between the Family Service of New Haven and the Family Counseling of Greater New Haven, Inc. (FCGNH). The series contains three sections: FCGNH records, scrapbooks, and transcripts.
  - Family Counseling of Greater New Haven, Inc.
    - Historical literature, time lines, and reports, 1931-1973, 1977, 1986, 1998 (Box 16, Folder 1-5)
    - News clippings, 1975-2000 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Newsletters, 1955-1983 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Professional and student papers
      - Erikson, Warren, "The need for direction: in families and family therapists", undated (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - Niederman, Miriam, "Unbroken Service", 1998 (Box 16, Folder 9)
      - Tran, Phuc, "Progressivism and social work in the 1920s: specialization, organization, social action and the Organized Charities Association of New Haven, CT", 1996 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Wessell, Irmgard R., "A family task: development of its sex value system", 1982 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Photographs and negatives, undated (Box 16, Folder 12-13)
    - Printed matter (Box 16, Folder 14-16)
    - Slides
      - "Depression and the Blues", 1997 (Box 16, Folder 17)
      - "Investing In Your Future: Employee Assistance Program" [Family Services America], 1983 (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Vol. 1, 1953 - 1963, Vol. 2 (Box 17)
    - Vol. 3, 1969 - 1972, Vol. 4 (Box 18)
    - Vol. 5, 1977 - 1983, Vol. 6 (Box 19)
  - Transcripts ["What's Your Problem?" column, New Haven Register]
    - 1963 - 1971 (Box 20, Folder 19-28)
    - 1972 - 1973 (Box 21, Folder 29-30)
  - Transcripts of newsclippings, 1963-1968 (Box 21, Folder 31-33)